Guide to the Records of the Sons of Temperance, Montauk Division 1836-1871 (bulk 1847-1860) MS 618
New-York Historical Society
Records of the Sons of Temperance, Montauk Division
1847-1871 (bulk 1847-1860)
New-York Historical Society
MS 618
0.5 Linear feet (1 box)
The Montauk Division was a regional branch, founded in 1844, of the Sons of Temperance, a fraternal order that assisted its members, both in remaining temperate, and as a mutual aid society. The records reflect the practical operation of a nineteenth-century fraternal organization and are composed of meeting minutes, committee reports, bills and receipts, printed circulars, letters, membership applications, inventories, proposed amendments, records of visitations to sick brothers and investigations of brothers.
Provenance
Purchased by the New-York Historical Society, March 21, 1945.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
The Sons of Temperance, a total abstinence society, was founded in New York in 1842. The fraternal order provided assistance for its members, both in remaining temperate, and as a mutual aid society. More broadly, they promoted the societal benefit of abstinence and temperance. The Montauk Division, a regional branch of the Sons of Temperance, was founded in Sag Harbor, in 1844.
In contrast to its immediate predecessor, the Washington Movement, the Sons recruited members from among those already well affected to their cause. Though they refrained from taking public stances on religious and political matters, they did advocate ending the temptation by stopping the production and sale of alcohol.
As a mutual aid society, the Sons of Temperance doled out sickness and disability benefits and allotted money to assist with the burial of fellow brothers and their wives. The attractiveness of its benefits led the organization to operate as a secret society, with stringent rules and a highly restricted membership. Allegations of intemperance and other transgressions were routinely investigated and often led to expulsion from the organization.
Though the Sons of Temperance survived through the Civil War, the Montauk Division ceased operation in 1865, replaced by the Agawam Division in 1867.
Missing Title
The Sons of Temperance, a total abstinence society, was founded in New York in 1842. The fraternal order provided assistance for its members, both in remaining temperate, and as a mutual aid society. More broadly, they promoted the societal benefit of abstinence and temperance. The Montauk Division, a regional branch of the Sons of Temperance, was founded in Sag Harbor, in 1844.
In contrast to its immediate predecessor, the Washington Movement, the Sons recruited members from among those already well affected to their cause. Though they refrained from taking public stances on religious and political matters, they did advocate ending the temptation by stopping the production and sale of alcohol.
As a mutual aid society, the Sons of Temperance doled out sickness and disability benefits and allotted money to assist with the burial of fellow brothers and their wives. The attractiveness of its benefits led the organization to operate as a secret society, with stringent rules and a highly restricted membership. Allegations of intemperance and other transgressions were routinely investigated and often led to expulsion from the organization.
Though the Sons of Temperance survived through the Civil War, the Montauk Division ceased operation in 1865, replaced by the Agawam Division in 1867.
Scope and Content Note
The records offer insight into the practical operation of a nineteenth-century fraternal organization. They cover aspects such as finances, the activities of the local division and wider organization, upkeep of the meeting hall, the management of its membership -- including investigations into allegations of transgressions of the group's rules and visitations, and payments to qualifying members. The records are composed of meeting minutes, committee reports, bills and receipts, printed circulars, letters, membership applications, inventories, proposed amendments, records of visitations to sick brothers and investigations of brothers.
Arrangement
The records are divided into series and arranged chronologically.
The records are divided into series and arranged chronologically.
Missing Title
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Fraternal organizations -- New York (State); Temperance -- Societies, etc. -- New York (State) -- Sag Harbor.; Minutes (administrative records); Temperance -- New York (State).; Cooke, Luther D.; Dean, Phineas; Eldridge, James N.; Gardiner, Adrian; Schellinger, D. W.; Sons of Temperance of North America. Grand Division of Eastern New York
- Series I: Correspondence, 1846-1858, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes incoming and some outgoing correspondence for the Montauk Division of the Sons of Temperance. Letters are from local members as well as other divisions in New York, Connecticut and Massachusetts.
  - Correspondence, 1846-1858, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
- Series II: Circular Letters, 1847-1853, undated
  These are printed circular letters from various divisions of the Sons of Temperance serving as notification of resolutions, amendments, invitations, and other business requiring communication to the wider organization.
  - Circular Letters, 1847-1853, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series III: Reports, 1846-1859, undated (Bulk 1849-1859)
  Within this series are Quarterly Reports, and reports generated by various committees and officers of the fraternity. Among these are the Finance Committee, the Treasurer, and the Conductor (this officer essentially gave an inventory of the division's hall), interspersed with reports from special committees dealing with issues such as the lease of the hall, the creation of a code of by-laws, the creation and printing of a seal, upkeep of the hall lamps, etc.
  - Reports, 1846-1852 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reports, 1852 July - 1859 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Applications and Certificates, 1846-1860
  These include two certificates attesting to the good standing of brothers leaving the division, meant to serve as recommendations to other Temperance divisions. The bulk of the series are applications from individuals interested in membership. Among these are women requesting to be admitted in an auxiliary capacity as "visitors." Applications contain recommendations of prospective brothers by existing members.
  - Applications and Certificates, 1846-1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series V: Health and Illnesses, 1847-1858
  Among these papers are letters from physicians attesting to infirmity of members, letters from brothers reporting the illness of a fellow member, and letters requesting benefits due for illness or disability. Also included are outgoing letters of condolence from the Sons of Temperance.
  - Health and Illnesses, 1847-1858 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Visiting Committee, 1855-1859
  In this series are records of visits made by the Visiting Committee, appointed to call upon sick members. The reports are made on pre-printed forms and include the identity of the member, the date he was reported sick, his condition during the visit, and a recommendation as to how many weeks of benefits he should receive.
  - Visiting Committee, 1855-1859 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series VII: Investigation and Disciplinary Papers, 1849-1859, undated
  This file contains documents relating to the fraternity's investigations into the behavior of its members, charges and disciplinary actions for non-payment of dues, and violations of the organization's ban on the consumption of alcohol.
  - Investigation and Disciplinary Papers, 1849-1859, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series VIII: Meeting Minutes, 1850-1852
  The meeting minutes only cover two years and appear to be rough notes of the proceedings. They are predominantly recorded in pencil and are crossed out, suggesting they may have been re-copied in a more formal manner.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1850-1852 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series IX: Proposals and Resolutions, 1852-1855, undated
  This series contains proposed amendments to the by-laws, resolutions made by the society and proposed preambles, all for the Montauk Division of the Sons of Temperance.
  - Proposals and Resolutions, 1852-1855, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series X: Bonds, 1846-1855
  This folder includes five treasurer's bonds, and one for a trustee. The documents were drafted to indemnify the Montauk Division against financial malfeasance, and stood until the treasurer or trustee had completed their duties and turned over all money and organizational material to their successor.
  - Bonds, 1846-1855 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series XI: Bills, Receipts and Checks, 1836-1871, undated (Bulk 1846-1860)
  The contents of this series cover the expenses for upkeep of the Sons of Temperance Hall, printing, postage and other expenses associated with the operations of the group. It is not clear whether the last few items directly relate to the Sons of Temperance but do appear to be promissory notes for one of its members.
  - Bills, Receipts and Checks, 1836-1851 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bills, Receipts and Checks, 1852-1871 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series XII: Fragments, 1838, undated
  Within this series are documents with little or no context, and in most instances do not appear to have any direct connection to the organization. The items seem to have been from the personal papers of an individual who maintained the Sons of Temperance records. They contain parts of a will, other official documents, poetry, mathematical calculations, and a list of names.
  - Fragments, 1838, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)